I think that is one step below the worst
case scenario. I think they're already
doing that. So, we should we should
expect to see that develop in the coming
years. But the worst case scenario
is that they come up with a unified
currency
and that countries around the world
begin to use that currency instead of
the dollar, especially with regard to
oil sales. The US empire ends the day
that that happens.
Ladies and gentlemen, welcome back to
Change Agents in Ironclad Original
presented by Firecracker Farm. Today's
episode is going to be a candid
conversation about various current
issues with a previous guest, John
Kiraau. And I'm going to be getting his
take as a former intelligence officer.
For those of you who haven't heard about
John, he is a former CIA officer who
gained prominence after he became a
whistleblower, revealing information
about the CIA's use of torture during
interrogations in the post 911 era. He
served as a CIA analyst and operations
officer specializing in counterterrorism
and the Middle East.
All right. They gave us a variety of
topics because I feel like you and I
could talk for about 18 hours.
>> Yeah, that's first for me. I I do I'll
sit here and talk all, you know, into
the night.
>> It's already 10:30 here, but it'll be
it'll be light until 10 or 11.
>> Yeah, but I mean, let's get some meat
and potato stuff in just in case the
lawyers need it. Um, okay. So, I need
you to put your agency hat back on here
for a second. I've actually and and I
hate this topic, but I'm going to ask
you about it. It involves Epstein,
right? Of course, there's wild
conjecture in every direction, but as
somebody
who's somebody who knows the
intelligence world well. I I'm not um
hugely conspiratorial. I do believe that
some conspiracies end up being true. And
that's actually why some of them can be
so sticky because there is an essence of
the truth and people can always say,
"Well, look at this one or look at that
one." I totally get it. But it's
interesting to me to see the buildup
about Epstein, especially in the current
administration's run for office. And
then all of a sudden it was if there was
a pop of a balloon and everybody is
supposed to believe that there was
nothing there. But the uh FBI will say
there's a 100,000 pages of documents.
And again, these are their words, not
me. So this is what the FBI has said.
Putting your hat on working in the world
of intelligence,
what would be your best guess as far as
who Epstein was and how he was
operating? Do you think he was working
adjacent to intelligence? Do you think
that people knew what he was up to, but
if he could provide information, they
would almost kind of give him a pass on
his behaviors, maybe clear the road in
front of him with not actually being
directly involved? And as somebody who
comes from that intelligence world,
would there have been any benefit to
using somebody like Epste, say, in the
role of a handler? You were at the top
of the source network. What could you
have done with somebody like him or what
would or would you have avoided somebody
like that just in general?
>> Wow, really great questions.
One of those questions is easy for me to
answer. One is very difficult. So the
easy one is I believe very strongly and
I've been public about this. I believe
very strongly that Epstein was an
Israeli access agent. And what an access
agent is, it's not like a normal
a normal like recruited asset who's
going to infiltrate a group or whatever.
It is someone who is someone who has
access to the actual targets. For
example, if Mossad wants highlevel
information,
it's it's not going to be able to
recruit Bill Clinton or Prince Andrew or
Bill Gates. Those people are not
recruitable. So, it does the next best
thing and it recruits somebody who has
access to those people.
>> Yep. And then just to make it just to
make the relationship a little richer, a
little deeper, you throw in underage
girls, free private jet, flights to a
private island, plenty of alcohol,
access to a lot of, you know,
interesting
people who are also important. And then
in the end, and we we know I should add
that literally every room in Epstein's
houses, including the bathrooms were
wired for both audio and video,
>> right? So, you're getting a massage from
a 15 or 16 year old girl.
>> They're going to he's going to hold it
in reserve just in case he needs to
squeeze you a little bit. The Israelis
are very, very good at that. So, um, to
me that's the easy question. I really
believe in my heart he was working for
the Israelis. The very difficult
question is
when he got the sweetheart deal as a
convicted pedophile in 2006,
>> this was down in Florida, right?
>> Florida in in the federal district
court. Um
he Alex Aosta the US attorney was told
to give him that sweetheart deal because
quote he's intelligence unquote. Okay.
What does that mean? He's American
intelligence.
He's Israeli intelligence, but the
Americans don't want to risk pissing off
the Israelis for some reason. or uh he
has something over somebody. I you know
I saw I saw a commentator the other day
make a very good point. The the point
the point was that
that there were only two people who
could order that sweetheart deal. One
was the attorney general of the United
States who was uh
what's his name? Gonzalez or whatever
whatever his name was, Bush's second
attorney general. Um, the only other
person was the president
and the attorney general is not going to
order a sweetheart deal for a convicted
child sex offender without clearing it
with the president. So why in the world
would George W. Bush
order house arrest for somebody who
convict who was convicted of a crime
that carries a mandatory minimum
sentence of 5 years in prison.
>> What did he have on George W Bush?
>> You know, going with that premise that
he was working for MSAD.
>> I I mean, I would like to believe that
our own intelligence agencies are sharp,
right? They're on the leading edge. I I
I I can't fathom that they wouldn't have
known about that,
>> right?
>> And so it's just so odd to me that they
would let him travel in such circles.
Not that they have a charter charter to
work obviously inside of the border,
right? The agency is supposed to be
external, but I feel like mechanisms
could maybe that's what I'm saying.
There's mechanisms like maybe, hey,
here's some information you guys might
want to look at. This person is
dangerous.
>> Yeah. Why wouldn't they do that?
>> You know, in any normal circumstance,
that that's an important point. In any
normal circumstance,
the FBI would have called Bill Clinton's
chief of staff or Bill Gates's, you
know, head of security and said,
"Listen, there's a potential problem
here. This Epstein guy, your boss should
stay away from him."
>> That's normally what they were do what
they would do. So why didn't they do
that in this case?
who made that decision that even after a
conviction which was in the papers it
wasn't a secret
even after this conviction
not only did did he maintain these
relationships he actually strengthened
and broadened these relationships how'd
that happen why wasn't the yeah warning
people
>> I and I think that's the pe the part
that for me that the gears don't mesh I
mean like you said what happened to him
in Florida there's actually entire
documentaries about that I I mean, a a a
sentence where you can actually go
wherever you want to during the daytime
and you have to come spend nights in an
unlocked prison cell. Like, basically,
you're sleeping at day camp. Like, what
the [__] And how and again, how did
that how did I mean, for myself
personally, I don't I don't judge how
other people want to live their lives.
And and I say this often, as long as
you're not praying upon people,
especially minors, I don't like people
have a lot of uh you know, when it comes
to Epstein, I would imagine that a lot
of what was happening was probably
people who were above age as well. Maybe
it was prostitution. And again, I that's
not my jam. But if people want to do
that, I'm not going to judge how they
live their life. They can suffer the
consequences of those
>> Yeah. of those behaviors. But I don't
understand how in me in my social circle
if I were to find out that somebody was
a convicted pedophile. I'm sorry. That's
a full stop right there. Period.
>> You got it.
>> What I would want to do is skin you live
with a potato peeler. I'm not going to
do that cuz I don't think I would enjoy
the federal penitentiary system. Nor do
I want to go there. But I can I can
manage the distance from that in my own
life via proximity and not having them
in those social circles. I don't
understand how somebody who had that
background was rubbing shoulders
literally and figuratively with some of
the most powerful and influential people
in this country.
>> Yeah.
>> And that's what I don't understand. And
then so that leads to well, why won't
they release the information? You know,
I I personally believe that it probably
would have non-flattering information on
both sides of the aisle, which is the,
you know, the reasoning why I think that
neither side really wants to release it.
But do you think that there is something
in that paperwork that if again going
off the premise that he did uh was an
agent for MSAD that exposes some level
of relationship that would be hard to
explain. Do you think there would be
something like that in those
investigative documents?
>> I think it's it's very possible and and
I'll I'll add something too w with a
little background first. When when
you're convicted of a federal sex crime
uh against a minor, there is a mandatory
minimum sentence of 5 years. Okay? It
doesn't matter if you're a good guy who
made one mistake or you're a bad guy who
made many, many mistakes.
Mandatory minimum sentence 5 years.
>> He did that. He got a what's called a
downward departure and a very serious
one. Secondly, pedophiles are not
permitted in minimum security work
camps, right? They have to be in low
security prisons. They normally don't go
to mediums or highs, maximums, because
it's too dangerous for them. So, they're
all in low security prisons unless they
killed the child, too.
So, how in the world was he able just to
walk out when he woke up in the morning,
go about his normal business, and then
go back to some, you know, Beverly Hills
Police Department style
uh uh luxury jail cell to spend the
night. I mean, that that had to come
directly from the top. Now, with that
said, I think the reason why we haven't
seen most of these 100,000 pages, in
addition to the fact that people on both
sides of the aisle are likely to be very
embarrassed and important people are
going to have their reputations ruined,
I think that we don't want to embarrass
the Israelis.
>> You know, I I'll give you another
example.
Buddy of mine, I'll give you two
examples. buddy of mine wrote a book uh
after but he he was my first boss at the
CIA. Prolific writer writes the most
fascinating books about the most obscure
20th century foreign policy and
intelligence issues. Wonderful. Great
readings
like who you would think I don't care
about you know US foreign policy toward
India during the Kennedy administration
and then you start reading it and you
can't put it down. That kind of book.
>> Wow.
>> Right. All right.
>> None of them are like that. He told me,
as we're all supposed to do, he sends
his books into the publications review
board for clearance.
And the only thing that they have ever
redacted were the words Israeli nuclear
program. Okay. The Israeli government
has never admitted that it has it has a
nuclear bomb.
>> Interesting.
>> Everybody in the world knows that the
nuclear bomb. So why is it incumbent
upon us to protect
Israel's policy of not admitting
to its possession of a bomb? I I didn't
sign a secrecy agreement to protect
Israeli classified information.
Um I I wrote a book on surveillance
and um I was writing about the history
of NSA and I said NSA
has cooperation with 33 countries um
including blah blah blah blah blah which
is like on their website
and only one word was redacted Israel.
Why
why is it
>> that's odd?
>> Yeah. I I I've never signed a secrecy
agreement saying I'm going to protect
Israel.
>> So, you know, I'm wondering if a lot of
this withholding of evidence and
withholding of documents is very simply
to protect the Israeli intelligence
apparatus.
Ladies and gentlemen, you've heard me
talk about Firecracker Farm and their
hot soul. You probably heard other
people talk about it as well. If you
haven't tried it yet, let me just tell
you, you're missing out on some serious
flavor. Their hot salt is delicious, and
it really makes pretty much anything
that you put it on even more delicious.
It's hot, but when you use it in
moderation, it's not too hot, and the
flavor that it adds enhances without
overpowering. It is handmade, super
premium, and comes in awesome stainless
steel push button grinders like the one
I have in my hand right here. You can
take them anywhere. Hot sauce, if you've
had this experience, can very easily
overpower other flavors and always runs
out quickly when it's good. Hot salt
lasts and lasts. The Push Grinder holds
over 500 plus pumps. And when you
consider the refill it comes with, it's
thousands of servings and it's a great
deal and a lot cheaper than the sauce.
For those of you that like flavor but
hesitate because it might be too hot,
you can mix it with sea salt to tone it
down and still enjoy the awesome flavor.
In my personal experience, you can
modulate how much comes out of the
dispenser. You're in total control of
the amount of heat you serve yourself.
So, if you would like to support our
show and give Alex and his family
business a shot, head over to
firecracker.farm
and use the code ironcloud to get a 15%
discount on your first order. You will
be very glad that you did. Firecrackerf
Yeah. Do you think it'll ever they'll
ever get a relatively large release of
those documents or do you think it'll
just be this 50 years from now this
trickle like the JFK files?
>> You know, I I want to believe Andy that
that there are enough people on both
sides of the aisle who are just sickened
by this whole case that they're going to
force release. And you know the law is
that any member of Congress can release
the information on the floor of the
House or the Senate, right? There is
some bipartisan movement towards this.
There's, you know, the Congress is in
recess right now, but they're going to
have an interesting September because
there are
>> both sides. I mean, I think actually
September 3rd, which is, wow, tomorrow
before this comes out.
>> But yeah, they're going to actually have
some Epstein victim testimony that is
released and the effort to try to bridge
the gap to the right hand side of the
aisle because I think they need six
signatures from the Republicans, then
they can force it. See, so if I I want
to believe
that
there's one person out of the 535 on
Capitol Hill who has the guts to stand
up and release this stuff. And deep
down, having served on both the House
side and the Senate side, I know that
there is no such brave person. I hope
that there would be, but I think we are
going to have to wait for that mandatory
declassification
35 years,
>> 50 years.
>> Nobody wants to, you know, nobody wants
to be found dead of the suicide with two
bullet holes in the back of their head,
>> right?
>> Like Frank Nitty, you know the story of
Frank?
>> No, but there's so many of these
ridiculous stories that it's like, come
on, I'm not that dumb.
>> Frank Nitty is is not an intelligence
figure. He was the under boss of the
Chicago syndicate under um Al Capone.
And when Al Capone was convicted of
income tax uh evasion and sent to
prison, Niti became the boss. He never
wanted to be the boss.
One of the things about Niti is that he
was deeply in love with his wife and
they had just adopted a baby boy and she
got breast cancer and died. So, here
he's he's left grieving, mourning with a
2-year-old. So, he got really really
drunk one day, went down to the train
tracks, put a gun up to his head, pulled
the trigger, the bullet went through his
hat,
so he decided to point it at his face,
fired a second time, it went through his
hat again.
>> Oh my god. Finally, he just sat down and
put it on his chest and fired a third
bullet and finally committed suicide.
And he's he's buried about 50 feet from
Capone in Chicago.
>> Man, man,
you know,
we got other topics other than Epstein.
I'm curious though again putting your
putting your intelligence hat back on if
you were if he was if Epste was there
for access and placement and you do get
compromising information on these
individuals or an individual of any
kind. How does it actually go? I'm sure
there's a variety of ways to do it, but
do you just hard confront these people
that you now have information against
and literally pull open a manila
envelope like they do in the movies and
you're flipping through pictures? Is it
more subtle? Does it depend on the
person? Because at some point, you're
probably going to want something from
them. How do you inform them that you
have the leverage that it is in their
best interest to do so?
>> Well, if it was you or me, it wouldn't
be settled at all. It'd be like an iron
fist,
>> like right on the nose.
>> Yeah. But if you're Bill Clinton or Bill
Gates or Prince Andrew or any of the
other, you know, Alan Dersawitz,
whomever,
>> um, yeah, it's going to be a very light
touch. You know, you put your arm around
it the guy around his shoulder and you
tell him what great friends you are and
we know how much you love Israel and and
we love you and so we we need for you to
answer a couple of questions for us.
>> Interesting.
>> You know, this is one
>> Yeah. I I learned early on at the agency
too, the soft touch is so much more
successful than than the the baldup
fist.
>> Yeah.
>> You know,
>> well, I think if you with the right
approach, you know, I probably the most
powerful way to do it is to basically
allow people to think it was their
decision in the first place.
>> Exactly. Right.
>> They may not even realize that they're
being leveraged.
>> A a good case officer would do exactly
that.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. I mean, at the end of the day,
when people are trying to sleep at night
staring at the ceiling fan, they know
what kind of kinky [__] they're into.
You know what I mean? They can connect
the dots on their own.
>> Even in training, even in training, they
they taught us not to make the actual
pitch until you were absolutely certain
that the target would say yes. And I
remember one of the instructors telling
me, you want the guy to recruit himself,
right? Because after a while, six
months, nine, 12 months, he's gonna be
pretty certain you're not who you
initially said you were.
>> But if he keeps up the relationship and
it's there's a benefit to him, 95% of
the time being financial, he's going to
essentially recruit himself. If you are
into quality gear and you are not
subscribed to Tacpack, well, then you're
missing out. Tacpack is a monthly
subscription box loaded with
professional-grade tactical gear from
trusted brands like Battle Arms
Development Neline 511 Tactical. You
have two options. You have the Tac Pack
Standard, which is a $59.95 shipped with
a value that usually lands between 90
and 120 bucks. Or you have the Tac Pack
Plus, which is $139.95 shipped, packed
with about $240 to $300 worth of gear.
But here's the kicker. The September Tac
Pack Plus is coming in hot, worth over
$330, and it's featuring a record amount
of gear. And right now, if you use the
code ironclad, you're going to get a
free tactical gift worth $70, bringing
your total value to over $400 just for
signing up. So visit tacpack.com, use
the code ironclad, and get the kind of
gear that doesn't just sit shelf.
What happens in that in the
statistically anomalous time period
where it goes wrong though? I mean,
what's the move there? Because doesn't
that expose the person that was kind of
pitching them or having that
relationship? Yeah.
>> I in in all my years at the agency, I
only saw it go wrong twice. Thank God.
It never happened to me. It happened.
>> I feel like it'd be a nightmare.
>> Oh, yeah. It happened once to a guy that
I was working with overseas. And, you
know, we we all read each other's
cables, right? And so we're we're giving
each other, you know, attab boys and you
know, go for it, man. When you meet with
AB butterfly on Friday night, we know
he's going to say yes, do it, dude.
You're going to get promoted.
And then the guy not only says no, but
reports you to his ambassador.
>> Oh boy. And then the prime minister
calls in the American ambassador
and this [__] hits the fan. I saw it
happen once and even headquarters wrote
back and said, "Wow, we we're shocked by
this. We thought he was going to say
yes."
So if it's It depends on the country
that you're in. If you're in a third
country, ah, you just say, "No, no, no,
no. I'm not a CIA officer." There's just
a misunderstanding.
How could you think I'm a CIA officer?
>> What's the matter with you?
>> So, you just don't see each other
anymore. You don't socialize together
anymore. If you're in the country where
the guy, you know, is a citizen of where
maybe he's in the foreign ministry or
the defense ministry, they're probably
going to expel you and and you have to
go back to headquarters and sit in a
penalty box for six or 12 months. Um, if
it's a hostile country, um, it could
become like a serious international
incident where they'll expel you and
maybe the station chief and then we have
to expel two of their guys and then it's
this tit for tat and it's all played out
in the press and everybody's going to
get screwed in the end.
>> Yeah, that that sounds like an absolute
nightmare. Yeah, people are going to
have some unscheduled moves. the moving
truck's going to show up to your
apartment and go ahead and pack your
stuff for you,
>> which happens.
>> I I bet it does.
>> You know, shifting gears.
>> When I was first when I was married, my
first wife, she was from Warren, Ohio,
and um we went back to the Greek
festival at St. Demetrius Greek Orthodox
Church in Warren, biggest Greek festival
east of the Mississippi River. So, it
was a big deal like for the whole
region. So, we would go back every year
and we're back there. It was like 1993,
I guess. And I see this woman like in
the in the line for a suaki or
something. And I recognize her from
headquarters.
So I walk up to her and I go, "Hey." And
she looks at me, she goes, "I know you."
I said, "Yeah, I know you too from uh
DC."
>> The place.
>> Yeah, that place
on the near side of the river. So, we
shake hands and she said, "What division
are you in?" I said, "I'm in uh in the
DI at the time, director of
intelligence. How about you?" She said,
"Oh, I'm in um whatever it was called
then." She's like, "I'm I'm getting
transferred to Moscow." I said, "Oh,
good for you. First tour overseas." She
said, "Yeah, I'm really excited." Well,
we didn't know that Aldra James had
already committed treason and had blown
her cover.
>> So, she gets to Moscow. She has very
heavy surveillance.
And then in the end, she and like six
other case officers are expelled.
It's in all the papers. Her name, her
picture, like going out to meet with a
source. It was a It was a disaster. She
gets expelled, comes back to the US. We
have to expel six Russians, which was
ugly. And then we cap we catch Aldra
James. He gets life without parole. We
have all these sources in in Russia that
are being executed. She ended up just
resigning and going to like Meil Lynch
or something. She's like, "This this is
[__] I'm not doing this anymore."
>> Well, how could she continue to do
anything covert anyway? I mean, if your
picture and true name is out there, I
mean, you're cooked.
>> Well, this is what happened to another
friend of mine, Mark Mark
Polymoropoulos. Mark and I were in the
DI together and then he switched over to
operations and specialized in um in uh
Eastern Europe and and
I guess the Soviet Union had just
collapsed and Ames blew him. So he had
to return from Moscow. Um they they call
it bringing them in from the cold. So he
came in from the cold, has all these
liaison jobs all over where you have to
be declared to every service because the
Russians have already blown your
identity to everybody anyway. And then
just to stick our thumb in the eye of
the Russians, we sent him back as the
station chief in Moscow and just said,
"Fuck you guys."
I guess that's one approach.
[Music]
>> You don't want to back away from that. I
fight on always. Scene 101 A, take
three.
>> If you're prepared for the worst case
scenarios, those worst case scenarios
are going to be manageable.
>> I got out because we weren't at war.
We're at war. I'm going back.
>> I want to quit like anybody else. I just
have the mentality I don't.
>> I thought I knew what the pain was up
until that moment. Accuracy is by far
the most important thing.
>> This community aided in who I am. It
gave me family. No fail is it's
everything. It's a way of life.
All right. Action.
[Music]
Well, I mean, on Okay, Russia. This
laterals me over to what else I wanted
to talk to you about as well. I'm not an
expert in geopolitics by any stretch.
I'm I'm a victim of the information I
consume. What's going on in Ukraine
between Russia and Ukraine and Trump's
role in that meeting with Putin in
Alaska? Then you know Zalinski comes
over to the United States and then I was
just reading so Putin Xi Jinping and
North Korea's Kim Jong-un are now all
going to gather in Beijing for this
major military event.
>> Yes. What do you what do you make of
what is going I mean are is everybody
playing every single side? Is this all
theater? What what do you make of what's
going on here?
>> No, I think this is actually quite
serious. Um, I I think the overall the
overall picture is actually
dark for the United States in that we
have used sanctions as a weapon on so
many countries over so many years that
these countries like Russia, China,
Iran, Cuba,
you know, even Pakistan and
North Korea,
South Africa,
they've all decided to work together in
part as what are now called the BRICS
countries plus all the new ones
>> um to come up with
I would call it even a a a parallel
global economy to the one that is more
or less headed by the United States.
I'll give you an example. Um, I have a
lot of friends who go to Iran. Some of
them are Iranian, some of them are I
mean Iranian-American. Some of them are,
you know, left-wing journalists who are
curious and they all come back and say
the same thing. The Iranians lack for
nothing. Our sanctions
haven't worked. And you see these these
numbum skull analyses from the likes of
the Henry Jackson Scoop Jackson
Foundation in London saying Iran's on
the brink of collapse. No, it's not.
It's doing just fine. Um, I'll give you
another example. I went to China last
year and I was struck by how difficult
it was for me to use my Visa card, but
everybody took this thing called the
octopus card. And so I asked one of the
shopkeepers. I was like, "What is this
octopus card?" He said, "Oh, it's it's
the Chinese credit card." I said, "Why
don't you just use a Visa card?" He
said, "Ah, because your credit card
transactions go through New York, which
subject us to sanctions. The Octopus
card goes through Shanghai, so we're not
in the hold of the Americans." And I was
like, "Right, I get it. I get it." So
you go to these countries like China,
even Russia, you know, the Russians were
were stung at first by the quickness of
our imposition of sanctions and then
they just turned to the Chinese, the
Indians, the other BICRICS countries.
They don't lack for anything. American
sanctions don't have any impact on the
Chinese on the on the Russians.
So I think that we put ourselves in a
corner.
>> What do you where
>> Yeah. No, go ahead.
>> Well, I was going to say, so what do you
make of Putin, you know, not that it's
necessarily out of his way to come to up
in Alaska and meet with Trump. Do you
think he's just Is he just wasting the
guy's time knowing that some I mean, I'm
assuming they didn't just put together
this meeting in uh Beijing. You know, he
probably knew he was going to go to that
before he even went and met with Trump.
Is it just a just to waste the guy's
time? Why do you think he even bothers
to meet with him?
Oh, I don't think it was to waste his
time. I think that they genuinely wanted
to feel each other out to see if there
was any wiggle room to come to a deal.
Remember, Trump is is, you know, all
about the art of the deal. And I will
say that during both the George W. Bush
and the Obama administrations and
frankly the Biden administration,
we used to marvel
at how hard these administrations worked
to not talk to our enemies, right? Let
the diplomats do what you're paying them
to do, to carry out diplomacy.
Why in the world would we not talk to
our enemies when talking and these open
lines of communication can only help?
So, one thing about Trump, he doesn't
care who he talks to. If he thinks
there's a deal at at hand, he's going to
talk. And I think that's what every
president should do regardless of
political party. So, I think that Trump,
you know, wanted to see if there was a
possibility to come to some sort of
deal. That's why he that's why he, you
know, softened up Zalinski in that very
well pre-planned humiliation in the Oval
Office a couple of months earlier. Uh,
>> you think that was pre-planned?
>> Oh, absolutely yes. 100% yes.
>> Do you think Zilinsky knew it was
pre-planned?
>> Uh, absolutely not. being blocked,
right?
>> Wanted to do an ambush.
>> And it was because Trump believed that
it was Zilinski blocking a deal
and then learned in Anchorage that it
actually wasn't Zilinski.
>> It's Putin blocking the deal. But at
least we know that now. It's important
to know that.
So, it was worth talking.
>> That's fair. And I totally agree with
you about being able to sit down and
talk with anybody about anything. I wish
people in our own country would actually
take that advice. I am so tired of
watching people
>> I can't talk to my family anymore. I
can't go to holidays and this that I'm
like are you kidding me? Like this is
your family and you're letting a
political belief and the the metric I go
back to and I try to remind people like
let's say [__] does hit the fan. say
that there's this unholy alliance of
Russia and China and North Korea and
whatever they do whatever your power
goes out for 96 hours which uh and I
always forget who the quotes associated
with but essentially you know chaos is
nine meals away and you're going to need
the guy across the street to help you.
You're going to need your neighbors to
rely upon and they might have had a
an election sign that was of a different
color than you may like but they're
still your neighbor. And if we can't get
and like, you know, it's it's the same
level just extrapolated to a
geopolitical level. Like, you need to be
able to talk to everybody. I talk with a
bunch of people that I don't agree with
on a bunch of things. And at the end of
the day, I leave hopefully with a better
understanding of why they believe what
they believe. It doesn't mean I have to
get on board, but at least I understand
where they're coming from.
I I couldn't agree more. I think you're
exactly right.
What uh what do you think would be worst
case if Putin, Xiinping and Kim Jong-un?
Would it be they create an alliance and
economy that rivals what is as you
mentioned largely led by the US at this
point and that grows to a size, scope
and scale that competes with and then
overtakes and then we find oursel
behind.
>> I think that is one step below the worst
case scenario. I think they're already
doing that. So we should we should
expect to see that develop in the coming
years.
>> But the worst case scenario
is that they come up with a unified
currency
and that countries around the world
begin to use that currency instead of
the dollar, especially with regard to
oil sales.
>> The US empire ends the day that that
happens.
>> Yeah, I had not even considered that.
Okay.
What uh how do you think the Ukraine
Russia conflict plays itself out? It's
it's fascinating. They'll talk about
having a ceasefire and then about five
minutes afterwards a missile or a drone
strike occurs and like why are we even
doing this anymore at this point? Just
keep blowing the [__] out of each other.
>> Yeah, I know, right? I I've been saying
the same thing for a long time and I've
been proven wrong so far, but I'm going
to double down and I'm going to say that
the way this ends is the way we've been
saying it was going to end since it
began. And that is with the Ukrainians
conceding territory,
the Donbass, Crimea,
as well as extracting a promise that
Ukraine will never join NATO, but then
allowing
or not objecting to Ukraine being
fasttracked for European Union
membership and then a declaration from
the United States that Ukraine will be
treated as what's called of a major
non-NATO ally like Japan, Australia,
Saudi Arabia, Israel. So, you
essentially get the same protections
uh that that a NATO membership would
give you, but you're not in NATO.
>> What do you think? Who do you think is
next in the wing after Putin moves
along?
>> You know, I don't think anybody knows
the answer to that. the the Russians had
uh Dimmitri Mediev for what is it four
years, six years and um he and Putin
just sort of they traded offices for one
term and then they traded him back
again.
>> So I I don't think there's any one
person waiting in the wings. I've I've
never heard that he has a protege, for
example, that he's grooming and and
frankly every time his term is up, um he
has the constitution amended to allow
him to run again,
>> of which he of course wins unanimously.
It's odd how that works out.
>> Yeah. Life is good,
>> man. What do you think will happen? What
whatever. I mean, you know, medical
things happen. If he were to drop dead
tomorrow, what do you do you think that
that would be a very tumultuous time in
Russia or do you think there'd be
somebody who would hop in and take it
over at lockstep?
>> I think it would probably be a military
person who jumps in and tries to keep
things as calm as possible. Um, Russian
friends of mine tell me that
most Russians support Putin just because
it's a time of war, but that deep down
he's not really that popular.
>> U, that wouldn't be terribly different
from what we see here in the United
States when we're involved in conflict
in one part of the world or another. So
were he to depart the scene, I think I
think there would probably be some kind
of quick early consensus and then a
transition into a democratic election.
>> Do you think it would change the the
future and trajectory of Russia or do
you think the status quo would largely
live on?
>> No, I think it's the status quo.
>> Interesting. Well, John, I want to be
respectful of your time. So, I got two
more questions for you and you can get
back to your joyous lawsuit because
they're so much fun
and these are broader and again this is
with your intelligence hat on or just
your experience throughout the world.
What is it that keeps you up at night if
you were to existentially worry a little
bit about what's going on in the world
for somebody like yourself who is in the
know about a lot of things that most
people don't have access to or
experience with? What uh what keeps you
staring at your ceiling fan?
You know, I think there are a couple of
things. I I've got a cousin that I'm
very very close to, and he said
something to me one time that I just
have no memory of. He said that in 2002,
he asked me the same question. And that
I said, a global pandemic.
And I said, "Did I really say that?" And
he said, "Yeah, and you talked about
SARS." I said, "Man, I don't remember
that at all." and he said, "Yeah, well
you turn
>> fortuitous."
>> Yeah.
>> So
that's one of the things that I worried
that I worry about and I worry about it
actually more now because now we know
that it's actually possible to have a
global pandemic. And we are more divided
about how we should respond to it now
than we were in March of 2020.
Hope you enjoyed today's show. If you
want to learn more about John's work,
please check out his show CIA
Declassified. Thank you again for
listening to Change Agents and Ironclad
Original presented by Firecracker Farm.
See you all next week with an all new
episode and an all new guest. See you
then.